<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-23T22:22:44+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">marcos oliveira | computational social science - complex systems - urban science - crime science - swarm intelligence | marcosoliveira.info</title><subtitle>Lecturer in City Science &amp; Analytics in the Department of Computer Science at the University of Exeter in the UK.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Larger cities, more commuters, more crime? The role of inter-city commuting in the scaling of urban crime</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/figures/2025/06/23/larger-cities-more-commuters-more-crime-the-role-of-inter-city-commuting-in-the-scaling-of-urban-crime.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Larger cities, more commuters, more crime? The role of inter-city commuting in the scaling of urban crime" /><published>2025-06-23T22:18:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-06-23T22:18:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/figures/2025/06/23/larger-cities-more-commuters-more-crime-the-role-of-inter-city-commuting-in-the-scaling-of-urban-crime</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/figures/2025/06/23/larger-cities-more-commuters-more-crime-the-role-of-inter-city-commuting-in-the-scaling-of-urban-crime.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="figures" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dynamic predictability and activity-location contexts in human mobility</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/predictability-states-in-human-mobility.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dynamic predictability and activity-location contexts in human mobility" /><published>2025-02-24T19:21:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T19:21:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/predictability-states-in-human-mobility</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/predictability-states-in-human-mobility.html"><![CDATA[<p>Human travelling behaviours are markedly regular, to a large extent predictable, and mostly driven by biological necessities and social constructs. Not surprisingly, such predictability is influenced by an array of factors ranging in scale from individual preferences and choices, through social groups and households, all the way to the global scale, such as mobility restrictions in response to external shocks such as pandemics. In this work, we explore how temporal, activity and location variations in individual-level mobility—referred to as predictability states—carry a large degree of information regarding the nature of mobility regularities at the population level. Our findings indicate the existence of contextual and activity signatures in predictability states, suggesting the potential for a more nuanced approach to estimating both short-term and higher-order mobility predictions. The existence of location contexts, in particular, serves as a parsimonious estimator for predictability patterns even in the case of low resolution and missing data.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Human travelling behaviours are markedly regular, to a large extent predictable, and mostly driven by biological necessities and social constructs. Not surprisingly, such predictability is influenced by an array of factors ranging in scale from individual preferences and choices, through social groups and households, all the way to the global scale, such as mobility restrictions in response to external shocks such as pandemics. In this work, we explore how temporal, activity and location variations in individual-level mobility—referred to as predictability states—carry a large degree of information regarding the nature of mobility regularities at the population level. Our findings indicate the existence of contextual and activity signatures in predictability states, suggesting the potential for a more nuanced approach to estimating both short-term and higher-order mobility predictions. The existence of location contexts, in particular, serves as a parsimonious estimator for predictability patterns even in the case of low resolution and missing data.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unravelling the dynamics of child sexual exploitation material circulation on the Dark Web</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/unravelling-the-dynamics-of-child-sexual-exploitation-material-circulation-on-the-dark-web.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unravelling the dynamics of child sexual exploitation material circulation on the Dark Web" /><published>2025-02-24T19:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T19:20:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/unravelling-the-dynamics-of-child-sexual-exploitation-material-circulation-on-the-dark-web</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/unravelling-the-dynamics-of-child-sexual-exploitation-material-circulation-on-the-dark-web.html"><![CDATA[<p>In recent years, there has been a significant increase in the detection of child sexual exploitation material (CSEM), with perpetrators increasingly turning to advanced encryption technologies to conceal their activities. This study delves into data from a Brazilian Federal Police operation on the Tor network, aimed at disrupting these illicit activities. We uncovered patterns indicating strong user preferences for certain content categories, suggesting the existence of distinct groups with shared interests. Additionally, our findings reveal consistent activity patterns among users, including specific 24-hour, 12-hour, and 6-hour consumption cycles. This research offers insights into the online behavior related to CSEM, providing a foundation for further investigation and the development of effective policy measures.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In recent years, there has been a significant increase in the detection of child sexual exploitation material (CSEM), with perpetrators increasingly turning to advanced encryption technologies to conceal their activities. This study delves into data from a Brazilian Federal Police operation on the Tor network, aimed at disrupting these illicit activities. We uncovered patterns indicating strong user preferences for certain content categories, suggesting the existence of distinct groups with shared interests. Additionally, our findings reveal consistent activity patterns among users, including specific 24-hour, 12-hour, and 6-hour consumption cycles. This research offers insights into the online behavior related to CSEM, providing a foundation for further investigation and the development of effective policy measures.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Systematic comparison of gender inequality in scientific rankings across disciplines</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/systematic-comparison-of-gender-inequality-in-scientific-rankings-across-disciplines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Systematic comparison of gender inequality in scientific rankings across disciplines" /><published>2025-02-24T19:05:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T19:05:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/systematic-comparison-of-gender-inequality-in-scientific-rankings-across-disciplines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/systematic-comparison-of-gender-inequality-in-scientific-rankings-across-disciplines.html"><![CDATA[<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> The participation of women in academia has increased in the last few decades across many fields (e.g., Computer Science, History, Medicine). However, this increase in the participation of women has not been the same at all career stages. Here, we study how gender participation within different fields is related to gender representation in top-ranking positions in productivity (number of papers), research impact (number of citations), and co-authorship networks (degree of connectivity). We analyzed over 80 million papers published from 1975 to 2020 in 19 academic fields. Our findings reveal that women remain a minority in all 19 fields, with physics, geology, and mathematics having the lowest percentage of papers authored by women at 14% and psychology having the largest percentage at 39%. Women are significantly underrepresented in top-ranking positions (top 10% or higher) across all fields and metrics (productivity, citations, and degree), indicating that it remains challenging for early researchers (especially women) to reach top-ranking positions, as our results reveal the rankings to be rigid over time. Finally, we show that in most fields, women and men with comparable productivity levels and career age tend to attain different levels of citations, where women tend to benefit more from co-authorships, while men tend to benefit more from productivity, especially in pSTEMs. Our findings highlight that while the participation of women has risen in some fields, they remain under-represented in top-ranking positions. Greater gender participation at entry levels often helps representation, but stronger interventions are still needed to achieve long-lasting careers for women and their participation in top-ranking positions.
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The participation of women in academia has increased in the last few decades across many fields (e.g., Computer Science, History, Medicine). However, this increase in the participation of women has not been the same at all career stages. Here, we study how gender participation within different fields is related to gender representation in top-ranking positions in productivity (number of papers), research impact (number of citations), and co-authorship networks (degree of connectivity). We analyzed over 80 million papers published from 1975 to 2020 in 19 academic fields. Our findings reveal that women remain a minority in all 19 fields, with physics, geology, and mathematics having the lowest percentage of papers authored by women at 14% and psychology having the largest percentage at 39%. Women are significantly underrepresented in top-ranking positions (top 10% or higher) across all fields and metrics (productivity, citations, and degree), indicating that it remains challenging for early researchers (especially women) to reach top-ranking positions, as our results reveal the rankings to be rigid over time. Finally, we show that in most fields, women and men with comparable productivity levels and career age tend to attain different levels of citations, where women tend to benefit more from co-authorships, while men tend to benefit more from productivity, especially in pSTEMs. Our findings highlight that while the participation of women has risen in some fields, they remain under-represented in top-ranking positions. Greater gender participation at entry levels often helps representation, but stronger interventions are still needed to achieve long-lasting careers for women and their participation in top-ranking positions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Larger cities, more commuters, more crime? The role of inter-city commuting in the scaling of urban crime</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/larger-cities-more-commuters-more-crime-the-role-of-inter-city-commuting-in-the-scaling-of-urban-crime.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Larger cities, more commuters, more crime? The role of inter-city commuting in the scaling of urban crime" /><published>2025-02-24T19:05:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T19:05:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/larger-cities-more-commuters-more-crime-the-role-of-inter-city-commuting-in-the-scaling-of-urban-crime</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/larger-cities-more-commuters-more-crime-the-role-of-inter-city-commuting-in-the-scaling-of-urban-crime.html"><![CDATA[<p>Cities attract a daily influx of non-resident commuters, reflecting their role in wider urban networks – not as isolated places. However, it remains unclear how this inter-connectivity shapes the way crime scales with population, given that larger cities tend to receive more commuters and experience more crime. Here, we investigate how inter-city commuting relates to the population–crime relationship. We find that larger cities receive proportionately more commuters, which in turn is associated with higher crime levels. Specifically, each 1% increase in inbound commuters corresponds to a 0.32% rise in theft and 0.20% rise in burglary, holding population constant. We show that models incorporating both population and commuter inflows better explain crime variation than population-only models. These findings underscore the importance of considering how cities are connected – not just their population size – in disentangling the population–crime relationship.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cities attract a daily influx of non-resident commuters, reflecting their role in wider urban networks – not as isolated places. However, it remains unclear how this inter-connectivity shapes the way crime scales with population, given that larger cities tend to receive more commuters and experience more crime. Here, we investigate how inter-city commuting relates to the population–crime relationship. We find that larger cities receive proportionately more commuters, which in turn is associated with higher crime levels. Specifically, each 1% increase in inbound commuters corresponds to a 0.32% rise in theft and 0.20% rise in burglary, holding population constant. We show that models incorporating both population and commuter inflows better explain crime variation than population-only models. These findings underscore the importance of considering how cities are connected – not just their population size – in disentangling the population–crime relationship.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stronger together? The homophily trap in networks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/stronger-together-the-homophily-trap-in-networks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stronger together? The homophily trap in networks" /><published>2025-02-24T19:04:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T19:04:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/stronger-together-the-homophily-trap-in-networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/stronger-together-the-homophily-trap-in-networks.html"><![CDATA[<p>While homophily – the tendency to link with similar others – may nurture a sense of belonging and shared values, it can also hinder diversity and widen inequalities. Here, we unravel this trade-off analytically, revealing homophily traps for minority groups: scenarios where increased homophilic interaction among minorities negatively affects their structural opportunities within a network. We demonstrate that homophily traps arise when minority size falls below 25% of a network, at which point homophily comes at the expense of lower structural visibility for the minority group. Our work reveals that social groups require a critical size to benefit from homophily without incurring structural costs, providing insights into core processes underlying the emergence of group inequality in networks.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While homophily – the tendency to link with similar others – may nurture a sense of belonging and shared values, it can also hinder diversity and widen inequalities. Here, we unravel this trade-off analytically, revealing homophily traps for minority groups: scenarios where increased homophilic interaction among minorities negatively affects their structural opportunities within a network. We demonstrate that homophily traps arise when minority size falls below 25% of a network, at which point homophily comes at the expense of lower structural visibility for the minority group. Our work reveals that social groups require a critical size to benefit from homophily without incurring structural costs, providing insights into core processes underlying the emergence of group inequality in networks.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Towards the identification of money laundering in bank transactions using Recurrent Neural Networks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/towards-the-identification-of-money-laundering-in-bank-transactions-using-recurrent-neural-networks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Towards the identification of money laundering in bank transactions using Recurrent Neural Networks" /><published>2025-02-24T19:03:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T19:03:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/towards-the-identification-of-money-laundering-in-bank-transactions-using-recurrent-neural-networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/towards-the-identification-of-money-laundering-in-bank-transactions-using-recurrent-neural-networks.html"><![CDATA[<p>Money laundering has a significant impact on both society and the economy, costing up to 2 trillion dollars of the global gross domestic product. Detecting money laundering involves analyzing banking data to identify its occurrence and its typologies, such as the typology I-d (i.e., fragmenting cash transfers to disguise the total value). The state-of-the-art detection methods can estimate the probability of classifying a client as suspicious based on financial reports, but they fail to identify specific typologies in a large volume of banking transactions and do not determine which transaction groups contribute to identifying a particular money laundering typology pattern. In this work, we propose automating the identification of money laundering typologies using banking transaction data represented as multiple time series. We use anonymized data provided from the Civil Police of the State of Pernambuco, Brazil, and trained recurrent neural network models to identify typology I-d in the data. The models include SimpleRNN, LSTM, and GRU. Our results show that LSTM and GRU models achieved the highest AUC-ROCs of 0.75 (0.74, 0.76). Our work demonstrates the potential for developing an automated tool to assist in identifying I-d typology, suggesting future work may focus on identifying other typologies and training models using different neural architectures.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Money laundering has a significant impact on both society and the economy, costing up to 2 trillion dollars of the global gross domestic product. Detecting money laundering involves analyzing banking data to identify its occurrence and its typologies, such as the typology I-d (i.e., fragmenting cash transfers to disguise the total value). The state-of-the-art detection methods can estimate the probability of classifying a client as suspicious based on financial reports, but they fail to identify specific typologies in a large volume of banking transactions and do not determine which transaction groups contribute to identifying a particular money laundering typology pattern. In this work, we propose automating the identification of money laundering typologies using banking transaction data represented as multiple time series. We use anonymized data provided from the Civil Police of the State of Pernambuco, Brazil, and trained recurrent neural network models to identify typology I-d in the data. The models include SimpleRNN, LSTM, and GRU. Our results show that LSTM and GRU models achieved the highest AUC-ROCs of 0.75 (0.74, 0.76). Our work demonstrates the potential for developing an automated tool to assist in identifying I-d typology, suggesting future work may focus on identifying other typologies and training models using different neural architectures.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Misinformation Dissemination: Effects of Network Density in Segregated Communities</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/misinformation-dissemination-effects-of-network-density-in-segregated-communities.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Misinformation Dissemination: Effects of Network Density in Segregated Communities" /><published>2025-02-24T19:02:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T19:02:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/misinformation-dissemination-effects-of-network-density-in-segregated-communities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/24/misinformation-dissemination-effects-of-network-density-in-segregated-communities.html"><![CDATA[<p>Understanding the relationship between network features and misinformation propagation is crucial for mitigating the spread of false information. Here, we investigate how network density and segregation affect the dissemination of misinformation using a susceptible-infectious-recovered framework. We find that a higher density consistently increases the proportion of misinformation believers. In segregated networks, our results reveal that minorities affect the majority: denser minority groups increase the number of believers in the majority, demonstrating how the structure of a segregated minority can influence misinformation dynamics within the majority group.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding the relationship between network features and misinformation propagation is crucial for mitigating the spread of false information. Here, we investigate how network density and segregation affect the dissemination of misinformation using a susceptible-infectious-recovered framework. We find that a higher density consistently increases the proportion of misinformation believers. In segregated networks, our results reveal that minorities affect the majority: denser minority groups increase the number of believers in the majority, demonstrating how the structure of a segregated minority can influence misinformation dynamics within the majority group.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Browsing behavior exposes identities on the Web</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/05/browsing-behavior-exposes-identities-on-the-web.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Browsing behavior exposes identities on the Web" /><published>2024-02-05T17:04:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-05T17:04:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/02/05/browsing-behavior-exposes-identities-on-the-web</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/05/browsing-behavior-exposes-identities-on-the-web.html"><![CDATA[<p>How easy is it to uniquely identify a person based on their web browsing behavior? Here we show that when people navigate the Web, their online traces produce fingerprints that identify them. By merely knowing their most visited web domains, four data points are enough to identify 95% of the individuals. These digital fingerprints are stable and render high re-identifiability. We demonstrate that we can re-identify 90% of the individuals in separate time slices of data. Such a privacy threat persists even with limited information about individuals’ browsing behavior, reinforcing existing concerns around online privacy.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How easy is it to uniquely identify a person based on their web browsing behavior? Here we show that when people navigate the Web, their online traces produce fingerprints that identify them. By merely knowing their most visited web domains, four data points are enough to identify 95% of the individuals. These digital fingerprints are stable and render high re-identifiability. We demonstrate that we can re-identify 90% of the individuals in separate time slices of data. Such a privacy threat persists even with limited information about individuals’ browsing behavior, reinforcing existing concerns around online privacy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Regularizing Neural Networks with Noise Injection for Classification of Brain Tumor in Magnetic Resonance Imaging</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/05/regularizing-neural-networks-with-noise-injection-for-classification-of-brain-tumor-in-magnetic-resonance-imaging.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regularizing Neural Networks with Noise Injection for Classification of Brain Tumor in Magnetic Resonance Imaging" /><published>2024-02-05T17:03:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-05T17:03:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/02/05/regularizing-neural-networks-with-noise-injection-for-classification-of-brain-tumor-in-magnetic-resonance-imaging</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/05/regularizing-neural-networks-with-noise-injection-for-classification-of-brain-tumor-in-magnetic-resonance-imaging.html"><![CDATA[<p>Overfitting jeopardizes deep learners dealing with noisy medical data. Despite its importance, our understanding of how neural networks generalize in medical imaging remains elusive. In this work, we propose to characterize the generalization profile of a model by evaluating its F1-score under data with varying noise levels. We use two architecturally distinct neural models, a Multilayer Perceptron (MLP) and a Convolutional Neural Network (CNN), to classify brain tumor in Magnetic Resonance Images (MRI) in a independent test data with different levels of salt-and-pepper noise. Our results reveal a clear distinction between the generalization profile of MLPs and CNNs. We demonstrate that shallow models can perform comparably to deep models when regularization is neglected. We also show that deep neural models benefit more from noise injection than shallow neural models, regardless of the differences between training and test data distribution. Our study sheds light on the nature of generalization in neural networks, laying the groundwork for further investigations of their underlying learning processes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Overfitting jeopardizes deep learners dealing with noisy medical data. Despite its importance, our understanding of how neural networks generalize in medical imaging remains elusive. In this work, we propose to characterize the generalization profile of a model by evaluating its F1-score under data with varying noise levels. We use two architecturally distinct neural models, a Multilayer Perceptron (MLP) and a Convolutional Neural Network (CNN), to classify brain tumor in Magnetic Resonance Images (MRI) in a independent test data with different levels of salt-and-pepper noise. Our results reveal a clear distinction between the generalization profile of MLPs and CNNs. We demonstrate that shallow models can perform comparably to deep models when regularization is neglected. We also show that deep neural models benefit more from noise injection than shallow neural models, regardless of the differences between training and test data distribution. Our study sheds light on the nature of generalization in neural networks, laying the groundwork for further investigations of their underlying learning processes.]]></summary></entry></feed>